James Dobbins Cartoons
James Dobbins Cartoons
1952-1971
Dobbins, James.
24 linear ft.
Original editorial cartoons, sketches and clippings.
148944
Biographical History
James J. Dobbins (1924-1994) was an American editorial cartoonist. He spent most of his career affiliated with Boston-area newspapers.
Born in Woburn, Massachusetts, Dobbins graduated from Woburn High School and attended Cornell College for a brief period before serving as a Navy flier during World War II, where he was awarded a Distinguished Flying Cross. After the war, Dobbins attended Massachusetts College of Art, graduating in 1951. He landed his first newspaper job with the Woburn Daily Times while still in college (1947-1949). Dobbins continued at the Boston University Graduate School of Education and worked as an English teacher in the Boston School System before signing on with the Lowell (Mass.) Sun as an editorial cartoonist (1952-1953). In 1953, Dobbins took a short term, 4 ½ week assignment with the New York Daily News while that paper's esteemed cartoonist, C. D. Batchelor, was on an extended leave of absence. When Batchelor returned, Dobbins continued to produce the Sunday drawing for another several months.
Dobbins began what turned out to be a steady run with Boston-area newspapers in 1954, when he took up with the now defunct Boston Post (1954-1956). Subsequently, Dobbins spent sixteen years with the Boston Herald Traveler (1956-1972) and another five years with the Boston Herald-American (1972-1977) before finishing his distinguished newspaper career with the Manchester (N.H.) Union Leader. In his retirement, Dobbins continued to produce cartoons, regularly contributing to the monthly publication of the National Association of Government Employees. James Dobbins died May 5, 1994.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The James Dobbins Cartoons collection contains original editorial cartoons, sketches and clippings of cartoons. For
Arrangement of the Collection
This collection is partially arranged—re-housing and complete inventory are pending.
Related Material
has collections of over one hundred cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Dobbins, James.; Boston herald traveler and Boston record American (Boston, Mass.); Boston post (Boston, Mass.: Daily); Lowell sun (Lowell, Mass.: 1888); New York daily news.; Art -- Cartoonists; American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Editorial cartoons -- United States.; World politics -- Caricatures and cartoons.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1953-1961 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1961-1963 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1963-1969 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1969-1974 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Cartoons (humorous images); Clippings (information artifacts); Editorial cartoons.; Sketches.; Cartoonists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of James Dobbins, 1967-1972.
Inventory
- Editorial cartoons (1968 accession)
  Click here for an itemized list of dates present for each year in this accession.
  - 1952 (Folder 1)
  - 1953 (Folder 2)
  - 1954, Jan-Jun 14 (Folder 3)
  - 1954, Jun 15-Dec 31, undated 1954 (Folder 4)
  - 1955 (Folder 5)
  - 1956 (Folder 6)
  - 1957, Jan-Jun (Folder 7)
  - 1957, Jul-Dec (Folder 8)
  - 1958, Jan-Jul (Folder 9)
  - 1958, Aug-Dec (Folder 10)
  - 1963 (Folder 11)
  - 1964 (Folder 12)
  - 1965, Jan-Jun (Folder 13)
  - 1965, Jul-Dec (Folder 14)
- Published cartoons (1978 accession)
  - Published cartoons (Box 1)
- Original artwork (1978 accession)
  - Cartoons, 1959-1960 (Oversize 1)
  - Cartoons, 1961-1965 (Oversize 2)
  - Cartoons, 1966-1967 (Oversize 3)
  - Cartoons, 1967 (Oversize 4)
  - Cartoons, 1968 (Oversize 5)
  - Cartoons, 1969 (Oversize 6)
  - Cartoons, 1970 (Oversize 7)
  - Cartoons, 1971 (Oversize 8)
  - Cartoons with rough sketches, 1967-1970 (Oversize 9)
  - Sketches (Box 1)
- Original artwork, later accessions
  - Cartoons, 1956-1957; eight editorial cartoons by James Dobbins pertaining to the connecting highway between Route 128 and Boston (Map-case 100)